Guide to the Karl and Ada Scheufler Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Karl and Ada Scheufler Papers
1921-1935
RG 25
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(9 boxes)
The papers provide excellent documentation of Methodist Episcopal Church mission work in Fukien Province during the first half of the 1920s. The internal workings of the Methodist mission, relationships with Chinese church workers, and the impact of political unrest are described in detail. Correspondence provides nearly weekly, detailed descriptions of the Scheuflers' life in China, including daily life and missionary work, evangelistic itineration, military and bandit activity, and Chinese festivals and customs. Karl William Scheufler (1898-1989) and Ada Mills Scheufler (1891-1958) served as missionaries of the Methodist Episcopal Church in Yenping, Fukien Province, China from 1921-1926. After returning to the U.S. in 1926 due to lack of mission funds and political unrest in China, Karl served as pastor of various churches in Ohio. During World War II, he served as a chaplain in North Africa, Italy and the Philippine Islands. Ada was a certified Director of Christian Education and was a Week Day Church School teacher in Cincinnati from 1942-1944.
Scheufler, Karl W.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jean Scheufler Johnson.
Biographical / Historical
1891 Feb 27 Ada Irene Mills born in Port Byron, New York, daughter of George and Carrie McMillan Mills
1898 Feb 6 Karl William Scheufler born in Sandusky, Ohio, son of Fred and Amelia Scheufler
1900s Ada graduated from Cortland (NY) Normal School and taught in New York State Public School system. She later graduated from the Chicago Training School, was consecrated as a Methodist deaconess, and worked in the Minneapolis-Chicago area. Karl attended Ohio Wesleyan University, Columbia University, Union Theological Seminary (NY), Harvard, and Boston University, receiving the A.B., A.M., and S.T.B. degrees.
1919 Ada received A.B. degree from Ohio Wesleyan University
1920 Ada received M.A. degree from Teachers' College, Columbia University
1920 Jun 23 Ada and Karl married. Children: Jean, Lowell, Elaine
1921 Karl ordained Elder
1921-1926 Karl and Ada served as missionaries of the Methodist Episcopal Church in China. After one year of language training in Nanking, they worked in Yenping, Fukien Province. Lack of mission funds and political unrest in China made it impossible for them to return to China after 1926.
1926- Karl served as pastor of various churches in Ohio. During World War II he was a chaplain serving in North Africa, Italy, and the Philippine Islands. Ada was a certified Director of Christian Education and was a Week Day Church School teacher in Cincinnati 1942-1944.
1958 Ada died.
1989 Karl died.
Scope and Contents
Though the Scheuflers were in China for a relatively brief period of time, their papers provide excellent documentation of Methodist Episcopal Church mission work in Fukien Province during the first half of the 1920s. The internal workings of the Methodist mission, relationships with Chinese church workers, and the impact of political unrest are described in detail.
The letters of Series I, Correspondence, primarily consist of letters written by Karl and by Ada to their respective families in the United States. Written in lieu of diaries, these letters provide nearly weekly, detailed descriptions of the Scheuflers' life in China. Besides describing their daily life and missionary work, including Karl's evangelistic itineration, the letters also make note of frequent military and bandit activity, Chinese festivals and customs, and so forth. Such topics are easily identified by stars of different colors and annotations on the Mylar sleeves in which the letters were placed by the Scheuflers' daughter.
The Notes and Writings of Series II include notebooks used in the study of Chinese, and narratives relating to trips and events experienced by the Scheuflers. Reports of mission work written by other Methodist missionaries are included in Series III, Collected Material. Also included in Series III are travel guide books used by the Scheuflers during their extended voyage back to the United States in 1926, and a wide variety of artifacts, including Chinese robes, decorative fabrics, bound foot shoes, woodblock illustrations, and so forth.
Karl Scheufler was an experienced amateur photographer and his interest in photography is evident in the many photographs found in Series IV. The photographs in the albums from Nanking, Peking, and Yenping are very well identified.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1921-1935, n.d.
II. Notes and writings, 1921-1926, n.d.
III. Collected material, 1921-1926, n.d.
IV. Photographs, 1921-1926, n.d.
Missions -- China; Missionaries; Scheufler, Ada Mills; Scheufler, Karl W.; Methodist Episcopal Church -- Missions -- China
- Correspondence, 1921-1935, n.d.; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Letters to Karl Scheufler's family, primarily written by Karl
  Letters to Ada Scheufler's family, primarily written by Ada
  Miscellaneous letters
  Within each of these sections, the letters are arranged chronologically.
  - Letters to Karl Scheufler's family (primarily written by KWS)
    - Written from Nanking, 1921 Sep-Nov (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Written from Yenping, Fukien Province, 1921 Dec-1922 Feb (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Incl. ten day trip to Peking, 1922 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Written from Yenping, Fukien Province, 1922 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Written from Kuling, 1922 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Written from Yenping, Fukien Province; includes "A Resume of the Political Conditions in North Fukien", distributed by the American Consulate 1922 Oct 19, 1922 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Written from Yenping, Fukien Province, 1922 Nov-1924 (Box 1, Folder 7-13)
    - Written from Yenping, Fukien Province, 1925 - 1926 Mar (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
  - Letters to Ada Scheufler's family (primarily written by AMS)
    - Written on voyage to Nanking from Nanking, 1921 Jul-Oct (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Written from Yenping, Fukien Province, 1921 Nov-1922 Apr (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
    - Written from Kuling (Jun, Jul), 1922 May-Jul (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Written from Kuling (Aug), incl. report by Karl re. Kiukiang Mutiny 1922 Aug 2, 1922 Aug-Oct (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Written from Yenping, Fukien, 1922 Nov-1923 Mar (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    - Written from Yenping, Fukien Province, 1923 Apr - 1926 Sep (Box 3, Folder 26-36)
    - Written from New York City, re. situation in China, 1926 Oct-Nov; 1927 Mar (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous:
    - One letter from Karl to Ada, while traveling, 1923 Jun 24 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - One letter from student to Ada, 1926
    - One letter to Ada and Jean from Laura, 1935 Apr
    - Four fragments, n.d.
- Notes and Writings, 1921-1926, n.d..; Series II
  - Notebooks used in learning Chinese
    - Notebook of Chinese vocabulary (AMS), ca. 1921. (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Notebook of Chinese vocabulary, ca. 1921. (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Notes/narratives:
    - "Christmas Reveries" (by AMS), 1921 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - "Country Travel" in Yenping Pagoda Herald (by AIS), 1926 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - "God, Some Folks, and a Centenary Evangelistic Fund" (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - "Hell Temple", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - "Peking Trip" (by AMS), 1922? (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - "Esther" (a play), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - List of books for children, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Collected Material, 1921-1926, n.d.; Series III
  The contents of the series are as listed.
  - Three issues of The Linguist, publication of the Nanking Language School, 1921,1922 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Typescript reports of work in Yenping Conference, by Glassburner, Reiman, Bankhardt, Skinner; map of Yenping Conference, 1921-1924, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Travel guide books: Federated Malay States, Java, Philippines, Hong Kong, ca. 1926 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Travel guide books: India, ca. 1926 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Pamphlets: "Missionary Bungalows"; University of Nanking Bulletin: Department of Missionary Training Announcements; Directory of Methodist missionaries; Calendar; Chinese language material; "Financial Notes" (Published by American-Oriental Banking Corporation), 1923-1924, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Map of Shanghai, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Passport of Karl Scheufler, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Photographs, ca. 1921-1926; Series IV
  The photographs are arranged in three sections: Albums, Loose photographs, and Negatives.
  - Photograph album - Vol. 1 - primarily Nanking, Peking, ca. 1921-1922 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Photograph album - Vol. 2 - primarily Nanking, Yenping (Fukien), ca. 1922-1923 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Photograph album - Vol 3 - primarily Yungan area, Yenping (Fukien), ca. 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Loose photographs - Chinese students and church workers, missionaries (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Loose photographs - Tinted scenes, primarily of Peking (See also: Oversize Box 3 - 5 black and white photos) (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Photographic negatives documenting journey from China to United States - in eight albums of 100, with identification, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 54)